Ryan Breed

Contact	Info
mail voice github	recruit@breed.org +1 (661) R-BREED-1 github.com/ryanbreed
linkedin	linkedin.com/in/ryanbreed

Overview

Seasoned security professional with 19 years of deep technical experience in security assessment, penetration testing, security monitoring, incident response, application security, and security architecture. I have a keen interest in practical applications of large-scale data analysis and infrastructure automation to increase organizational resilience to cyber attacks and other major disturbances. I also have practical experience automating Cyber Threat Intelligence sharing and organizing collective security initiatives through cooperative information sharing with public and private sector entities.

Education

- University of Texas at Austin LBJ School of Public Affairs Global Policy Studies (2012–2014)
- University of Rochester Bachelor of Science in Molecular Genetics 1997

Experience

Principal, Critical Infrastructure Security

Electric Reliability Council of Texas (ERCOT) Nov 2012 - Oct 2016

Individual contributor responsible for engaging business units to develop strategic opportunities for improving grid and market systems while delivering on key security initiatives.

Key Responsibilities

- Senior Incident Responder: provide investigation and analytical support for critical incidents.
- Network Defense Hunt Mission: develop novel analytics for event data. Exploit home-field advantage to degrade adversarial mobility and freedom of action.
- Intelligence Lead: prioritize collection and analysis projects. Develop strategic plans for threats to critical grid and market systems.
- Technology Lead: Research and implement emerging technologies for application to business and security challenges.
- External Interface and Advocate: Perform outreach to public and private sector via ISO/RTO council and DHS CISCP. Engage in public speaking to advocate for electricity sector needs and share information and practices.

Major Accomplishments:

- Automated real-time integration of CMDB, IPAM, access control, and vulnerability data into machinereadable representation of entities, applications, business systems, and infrastructure.
- Automated defensive countermeasures. Used model data to safely deploy automated containment, investigation, and other response countermeasures in response to automated threat detection analytics.
- Implemented TAXII endpoint to ingest STIX cyber threat intelligence feeds and propagate indicators to monitoring and control surfaces.

- Developed security testing for Continuous Integration. Used Bamboo to automate Nexpose for vulnerability and baseline assessment. Security findings over a project-specific risk threshold triggered a build failure and intiated response notification chain.
- Developed automated report and security finding distribution. Management reports were automatically updated and reconfigured based on changes to underlying assets and changes in responsible parties.
- Developed Ansible playbooks for CIS benchmarks and Nexpose vulnerabilities. Automated compliance
 artifact creation and remediation of findings in dev/test environments. Tickets for specific findings were
 dispatched to responsible parties where human intervention was required.
- Implemented ELK stack for monitoring BroIDS, auditd, RSA Netwitness, and ArcSight ESM/Connector logs. Developed custom logstash plugins to enable event ingest from CMDB and ArcSight.
- Implemented Telegraf, InfluxDB, and Grafana to translate event data into time series domain for tracking metrics and developing new analytics. Collected system telemetry with telegraf to enable performance analysis.
- Developed scenario and training injects for GridEx III. Developed cyber simulator and ChatOps platform for use during exercise play.
- Developed Big Data test bed deployed DataStax Enterprise Cassandra, Hortonworks Hadoop, Apache Spark, GraphLab, Neo4j, and JupyterHub environments loaded with data from IT, market, and grid systems. Developed proof-of-concept analyses showcasing each technology platform for evaluation by business and IT owners.

Manager, Critical Infrastructure Security

Electric Reliability Council of Texas (ERCOT) Dec 2009 - Nov 2012

Managed a team of 9 security analysts to cover security operations, monitoring, incident response, compliance controls, and security architecture.

Key Responsibilities

- Managed departmental budget, including annual and quarterly forecasting. Developed and presented project proposals for cyber security initiatives.
- Provided guidance and oversight in the capital project process to ensure security objectives were incorporated into investment initiatives.
- Lead audit response efforts for cyber security control activities in NERC CIP and SAS70 compliance programs.
- Managed tasking and tracking to remediate findings from audits and other outside assessments.
- Managed employee performance and aligned career development goals with strategic department objectives.
- Developed working threat model for market and grid operations to guide strategic planning.
- Developed, maintained, and exercised Disaster Recovery and Business Continuity plans for cyber security systems.
- Contracted outside penetration tests and assessments to proactively identify and remediate security issues in business and IT systems.
- Lead participation in public/private partnership projects with DOE and DHS.
- Attained SECRET clearance under DHS Private Sector Clearance Program and attended threat briefings as necessary.

Major Accomplishments

- Led implementation of DOE ESNM/CRISP pilot site and participated in program development workshops.
- Developed automated security advisory analysis system to triage, score, and dispatch vendor advisories and vulnerability notifications.
- Represented Cybersecurity Department in GridEx II Exercise Play.
- Represented Electricity Subsector in classified threat workshops for IC at DOE INL.

Lead, Security Operations

Electric Reliability Council of Texas (ERCOT) Dec 2005 – Dec 2009

Performed security monitoring, incident response, and investigations.

Key Responsibilities

- Infrastructure design and implementation for SIEM, IPS, IDS, Enterprise Forensics, full-content packet capture, web content filtering, and vulnerability management.
- Workflow development for security operations, monitoring, and investigation processes. Developed dashboards, reports, and incident documentation templates. Documented procedures and created reports for compliance controls.
- SIEM content development for automated analysis of security events.
- IDS/IPS signature development to incorporate cyber observables extracted from investigations into real-time monitoring functions.
- Perform forensic analysis of incident artifacts and other digital evidence. Develop incident reports and brief management on findings and recommended response actions.

Major Accomplishments

- Deployed 2 major iterations of ArcSight ESM
- Integrated ArcSight ESM with IBM/ISS IPS, Snort NIDS, Tenable Nessus, Windows Events, UNIX/Network/Firewall Syslog, Oracle RDBMS, Microsoft SQL Server and Symantec Antivirus.
- Developed automated analysis tools for decoding malicious javascript extracted from network traffic.
- Developed full-content packet capture and indexing system to extract packet captures indexed on time and IP address.
- Developed management application for BlueCoat site categorization via local policy database.

Security Consultant

Unisys Mar 2003 - Dec 2005

- Performed security assessments, penetration tests, and risk assessments for clients in the Financial Services, Health Care, Manufacturing, and Public sectors.
- Wrote and presented post-engagement reports to clients and provided guidance for addressing findings in line with business objectives.
- Developed labor models and project materials to support pre-sales and standardize engagement delivery across the security practice.
- Developed application penetration test capabilities and assessment framework for other consultants within the practice.
- Directed team activities for large assessments and security infrastructure implementation projects.

Senior Staff, Security Engineering

Zurich Global Assets Jun 2002 – Feb 2003

- Developed Security and Network Operations Center for ZGA infrastructure.
- Acted as ZGA divisional representative at Zurich Financial Services Global Information Technology Services activities.
- Performed security assessments on ZGA and ZFS infrastructure.
- Administered local IDS, Firewall, and UNIX systems.
- Performed local security monitoring.
- Lead global security monitoring team (Dublin, Zurich, Schaumberg, New York, Los Angeles) across ZFS divisions.
- Lead the global PKI implementation team.

Technical Services Director

ThruPoint Oct 1999 - Jun 2002

- Performed security assessment, penetration test, infrastructure design, and infrastructure implementation projects for clients in Financial Services and Media sectors.
- Served as final internal point of escalation for all security consulting technical matters across the company.
- Developed security test lab for use by other security consultants.
- Directed security projects for large engagements.
- Provided staff skills development assistance for other security consultants.

Security Consultant

Securities Industry Automation Corporation (SIAC) Oct 1998 – Sep 1999

- Did first shift firewall operations for Gauntlet firewalls on the internal perimeter networks.
- Performed start-of-day and end-of-day procedures to ensure continuity of operations for second and third shifts.
- Did requirements analysis for business requests and implemented subsequent infrastructure changes.
- Performed UNIX system administration tasks to support maintenance activities
- Participated in Y2K readiness preparations for NYSE security infrastructure.

Security Consultant

Interactive Futures May 1997 - Sep 1998

- Performed security assessments for clients in the Media, Legal, and non-profit sector
- Designed and implemented CheckPoint and Gauntlet firewalls for VAR customers.
- Designed and implemented Sun Solaris/SPARC systems for VAR customers.
- $\bullet\,$ Supported pre-sales discovery and developed written responses to RFP solicitations.

Certifications

- Completion of Advanced Training Mercedes AMG Driving Academy
- Leadership Skills for Managers Certificate Program University of Texas at Austin Professional Development Center
- Advanced SCADA Security Idaho National Laboratory National SCADA Test Bed
- Certified SCADA Security Architect Digital Bond, Inc.

Courses

- Microsoft Windows Security (SANS-505)
- Reverse-engineering Malware (SANS-610)
- PowerShell (SANS-537)
- Identifying and Removing Malware (SANS-537)
- ArcSight ESM 6.5 Security Administrator and Analyst (HPE-00924200)

Awards

- Team Player Award ERCOT March 2016
- 1st place Team Autocross Mercedes AMG Driving Academy June 2015
- Core Value Award for Expertise ERCOT April 2014
- Team Player Award ERCOT April 2014
- Exceptional Performer Award ERCOT January 2014
- Certificate of Recognition: Principal, Critical Infrastructure Security ERCOT December 2012

- Team Player Award ERCOT July 2011
- Team Captain and Winning Team Idaho National Laboratory NSTB Advanced SCADA Security Training November 2008

Skills

- Security: ArcSight ESM/Logger, Bro IDS, McAfee Network Security Platform, Suricata IDS, RSA Security Analytics/Netwitness, Carbon Black Protection (Bit9 Parity), AppLocker, SILK, Netflow, Gigamon
- DF/IR: Volatility Framework, plaso/log2timeline, EnCase, F-Response, Carbon Black Response, Soltra Edge, STIX/CybOx/TAXII/OpenIOC, Cuckoo Sandbox, McAfee Advanced Threat Detection
- Vulnerability Management: Rapid7 Nexpose, RedSeal, Tenable SecurityCenter, MetaSploit Pro, PhishMe, OpenSCAP, SCAP/OVAL/XCCDF, Scumblr
- Crypto/Secret Management HashiCorip Vault, Microsoft Certificate Services, cfssl, OpenSSL, PKCS11, TPM
- Automation/Management: packer, Chef, Ansible, Consul, ActiveDirectory Group Policy, Apache ZooKeeper
- Languages: Ruby, Python, R, Shell/Bash, PowerShell, Go/golang, Scala, JavaScript
- Workflow: JIRA, SharePoint, Confluence, HipChat, rundeck, Stash, Bitbucket, git
- Testing: jenkins, TravisCI, Bamboo, selenium, cucumber, rspec, serverspec, brakeman, rubocop, capybara
- Data Repositories: MySQL/MariaDB, PostgreSQL, Cassandra, ElasticSearch, InfluxDB, OSISoft PI System
- ETL/Pipeline: Apache Kafka, RabbitMQ, Logstash, Pentaho Data Integration, Flume, Sqoop, Avro, Parquet
- Monitoring/Metrics: Telegraf, Kapacitor, Zabbix, Nagios, CollectD, DiamonD, StatsD, Graphite, jolokia, jmxtrans
- Web: Apache HTTPD, nginx, varnish cache, squid, haproxy, traefik
- Virtualization: VMWare ESX, Docker, QEMU, KVM, OpenStack, Vagrant, AWS EC2
- Analysis/Visualization: Jupyter, Rstudio, Apache Spark, Tableau, Pig, pandas, scikit-learn, shiny, grafana, kibana
- Compliance: NERC CIP, SSAE16, NIST SP800-53, NIST CyberSecurity Framework
- OS: CentOS/RHEL 5-7, Windows Server 2008/2012, macOS, OpenBSD, FreeBSD
- Network: Cisco IOS, Arista EOS, openvswitch, ISC BIND, AWS Route53, InfoBlox DDI, wireshark
- Storage: ceph, minio, OpenStack Swift, AWS S3